So just as a reminder,
we are starting the meeting.
I'm admitting everybody who is in the
waiting room.
Good afternoon everybody.
This is we are just admitting everybody
from the waiting room.
It does take a couple of minutes for that
to occur.
And so while that's happening,
just as a reminder,
my name is Dominic Serlo with the New
Mexico Department of Health.
I'm the Center Director for medical
cannabis and psilocybin.
And this meeting is being recorded.
And this is the Propagation committee
meeting with Chris Pisguski as the chair.
And with that,
I will turn it on over to you, Chris.
Thank you.
We just started and I saw Greg has his
hand up.
But you know, we,
we usually start these meetings with the
30 seconds of silence just to try to
center ourselves and create a small
container of calm in a world full of
chaos.
So you'll stick with me for 30 seconds?
All right.
Thank you everyone for that and I started
to pick on you, Greg.
We'll get to questions in a minute,
though.
I called this meeting just so we can all
gather information about the next step
with the rules hearing and so we can
maybe talk about some of the things that
we've seen individually so that we can
collectively, I guess,
advocate for them at the rules hearing.
And but a lot of this is I just wanted to
get people to understand how this process
is,
is moving forward and how they can
continue to be involved and what the next
steps are.
So with that said,
would you like to give a program update,
Dominic?
Sure, absolutely.
So as everybody knows,
so with the rule hearing is going to be
on Friday, April 24th starting at 9:00 AM.
It is a hybrid meeting,
so people are welcome to come in person.
It will be held in the auditorium at the
Reynolds Building in Santa Fe that's at
1190 Saint Francis Ave.
in Santa Fe.
Or you'll be able to join,
register and join virtually.
And so for people who are not able to
travel or be there in person for a
variety of reasons,
you can still join in and participate.
And so really that's our our big aspect
of what's going on right now.
The program has been meeting and I've
announced some of this and some of the
other.
Forgive me if I am duplicating,
but in other meetings,
but we've been meeting with HCA with
regard to potential billing ability
during sessions and what exactly that
would entail and what would and would not
potentially be covered.
That's going to be very key and important
with regard to as far as licensures for
various licensed healthcare providers
such as licensed counselors, therapists,
social workers, MD's, etcetera.
And so we're working with them with
regard to that,
that they'll be more information in the
Education and Training committee.
We are actually participating in a tribal
listening session,
which is happening next week on the 22nd
and 23rd,
where we'll be presenting and hearing
from, well,
presenting to and hearing from tribal
administrators with regard to the
psilocybin program.
And so helping to move forward and
ensuring that there's a safe place for
people to provide information.
And in addition to that,
just the number of committee meetings,
there's quite a few coming on up and
we'll put those in the chat here in just
a minute.
And then otherwise,
I think everything else is around the
hearing.
And so Chris,
would you like me to just dive into sort
of what the hearing entails and how that
works and that aspect?
Or are there other items you want to talk
about first?
No,
that was going to be my next questions
actually.
Like what two people expect?
Are there going to be time limits?
Would they better be off be better off
putting in longer comments?
And before we move to that though, I,
I did have one question about the tribal
listening session.
Is that a closed meeting or is that
opening to the public as well?
That,
that actually was by invite for the
tribal administrators that work through
our, our, that,
that has come through our Office of
tribal liaison.
So that is not open.
I, I'm not sure who else is invited,
but I do know it's tribal administrators
so that they can start participating.
We do anticipate having additional public
sessions,
but limited for a tribal members to
ensure that they're safe spaces.
Absolutely.
I agree wholeheartedly and hopefully
Desbaugh gets to go.
The only thing I'll add to that,
so I believe Jorge has posted a copy of
where people can find the the notice and
the text of the proposed rules.
It's at HTTP: backslashbackslashnmhealth.
org\ about\ ASD\ CMO\ rules\ And here he
he could just put it in the chat again.
Thank you.
And so that's where you can find it.
What do people expect when they get there?
OK,
so essentially what happens with the rule
hearing?
And and this by the way,
we've actually had it in various
newspapers,
we've talked about it in other meetings
with regard to it,
and we do anticipate and actually
encourage for there to be public comment
regarding it.
Now the the hearing officer usually will
set a time limit with regard to public
comment.
Each individual user usually getting a
set amount of time and that time is often
either 3 to 5 minutes.
So just be prepared for that aspect once
the public comment section of it the
hearing starts.
But the way the hearing,
usually the way the hearings are
structured is once the hearing is called
to order and is made public.
So everybody let in through the the
virtual link and for the people who are
present is the hearing officer has some
formal aspects that they have to go
through and announcements things like
that.
And then the next step is that the
hearing officer will ask for the program
to provide any potential changes and a
brief overview of the rules from when
they were published.
Now one of the things that does occur in
the time frame between when we published
the rules.
Now I should make sure to every that
everybody understands publishing them
just means making them public.
It's not the final rule set.
Promulgate is the term that is used once
they get into effect.
And so for the once they were published,
we have been receiving and some public
comment on it.
And with that,
there are mistakes that we made in the
rules, slight changes that need to happen,
other areas or sections that need to be
addressed a little bit more that will all
be announced and discussed at the
beginning of the rule hearing.
So what'll happen is either myself or
Jorge will go through all of the
different potential changes from what was
originally published to what is being
presented at that time.
We are working and, and,
and so we are working as public comment
comes in.
We know there's been some that we've
received especially in the last couple of
days to compare it to the rule in C Does
this make sense?
Does this change for example in wording
or what somebody has proposed as a
difference in process procedure etcetera.
Does that make sense and do we need to
look at changing it?
And so those processes are going on right
now and,
and that will all be discussed and
announced at the beginning of that rule
hearing so that everybody who is there
knows.
So if a part, for example,
say there is a particular definition that
you're, you know, that you think, oh,
that should change.
And if you hear in the very beginning of
the hearing that, oh,
we've actually changed that definition
because we already got that feedback,
you can then modify your public comment.
If you're doing it verbally during the
hearing,
you can modify your comments so that you
have time to focus on some of the other
examples.
So that way you understand and,
and can hear what are the differences
that have occurred from the publication
until the hearing itself now.
And then once that portion is done and
all of these are submitted as exhibits.
And so all of this becomes a part of the
record for the hearing.
And then essentially the vast majority of
the meeting is usually public comment.
And that is the point where people and
individuals can go ahead and turn around
and express their thoughts,
opinions and ideas with regard to the
rules.
Now, some of it I will be very honest.
During previous rule hearings,
we could quite often hear about things
that just are not possible under a
particular statute or are outside of the
purview of the department.
And that's perfectly fine.
Just realize that there may be items that
we don't have any particular way to
change because they are in statute or
outside of our jurisdiction.
I hope this all makes sense.
I,
I'd like to stop right now and just to
make sure and see if there are any
questions about this.
So far I'm not seeing any hands.
OK, well,
I'm glad that I'm explaining it well,
but if people do have questions about it,
you know, please don't hesitate.
If you think about it in the next few
minutes during this meeting,
please also don't hesitate.
Now the other part I just want to talk
about,
and this seems to be something that again,
as we've talked about it in some of the
meetings,
but it seems to be a part that people are
a little confused and if kind of
overlooked.
And that's OK.
There's a lot going on with this.
And so that's easy to do.
And the main part about that is some
people have made comments that they want
to change the definitions for things like
the practitioner,
the guide and all of that.
And what I just want to make sure is
clear is those aspects that really are
about the therapy and the administration
side are actually there as placeholders
because they are mentioned in this rule.
Because for example,
when the psilocybin is transported from
the cultivator to the practitioner or the
approved location,
there had to be a essentially A
placeholder definition.
As some of the other committees,
especially training and education,
where they're looking at what levels of
licensure for practitioners and
clinicians and,
and those sort of things where those are
going to be,
those definitions are going to change
because that is a part of that purview of
that committee.
But because those individuals are
mentioned within this rule,
we had to have placeholders.
So if you're looking at some of those
definitions,
please do still make the public comment
because that public comment can actually
go to the committee.
As far as looking at for the next set of
rules on what gets changed on it.
These rules really are focused on the
aspects that are that surround
cultivation, transportation, and testing.
So if the other part is that you have a
lot of time,
you have a lot of other things and
priorities in your life,
which I know everybody does,
and you want to focus in as far as the
rule,
the parts to look at and really take more
time on.
Those are the three areas to really focus
on.
And again,
because some of those definitions are
there as placeholders,
but if you're not sure which ones,
please go ahead and provide that comment
because, again,
that can be very useful still with regard
to the other committees as they look at
those aspects of treatment and education
and training.
And I hope that part's making sense.
And that mostly primarily, by the way,
is just within the definitions.
Any questions so far?
No, I think that helps a lot, Dominic.
I know there's been some confusion about
that and why those definitions were put
into place because we hadn't really
decided in the Advisory Board about that
yet.
So that's very helpful.
Please forgive me,
I'm on A I'm on a 2 1/2 K fast,
so I'm about 3/4 of the way through it.
My brain's not working as well as it
normally does, but what are?
So what's the next steps after this rules
hearing?
When will people be able to go to these
promulgated rules and know, you know,
how to proceed with starting their
cultivation business?
Great question, Chris.
So some of that depends on how much
comment is received.
What occurs after the rule hearing is the
hearing officer then takes the entire
compilation of public comment,
both verbal and written and essentially
creates a report which will be made
public.
And then from that point, for example,
if they,
if the hearing officer says the only
changes in it are, you know,
you accidentally put a couple of extra
numbers or transpose some letters,
then we would make those minor fixes and
promulgate the rules.
I anticipate it'll be a little bit more
than that because there are a lot of very
passionate people and we're going to have
ideas that will come up that may not have
been thought of or brought up in
committee meetings before.
So with those, then we'll look at them.
We'll consider them.
Do they fit within the processes?
Do we need to make adjustments?
If there are a few adjustments but not
items that are made to be major,
then what can happen is then the rules
will get it at that point.
But that process depends a lot upon how
long it takes the hearing officer to go
through them.
And so it could take the hearing officer,
depending on the volume, a week, 2 weeks,
3 weeks.
We don't have,
and we won't know the answer to that
until they give us an ETA.
But as soon as we have information
regarding that,
then we'll be able to move forward with
letting people know.
Once we get that from the hearing officer,
and if there are no major changes,
then what occurs is we have to publish it
in the register, the rules themselves.
And once they're published,
at that point that publication becomes
the promulgation of the rules.
And so that promulgation then will will
mean they're in effect.
Once they are in effect,
the department as part of it needs to
ensure that we have the applications up
and available so that anybody who is
looking at cultivation or testing will be
able to apply.
And the deadlines and dates as far as
that application,
we anticipate the initial ones, you know,
to receive those initial ones within that
first month.
There's not going to be a due date per SE
for applications with regard to either of
those, those categories.
What it really would just be as we may
have a best to apply by for or for best
consideration or early consideration
because what our goal is,
is to ensure that we have enough
cultivation for those initial patients by
December and the same with regard to
testing.
And so we will continue to process
applications, but the more that we get in,
the longer that's going to take to go
through them all.
Now,
unlike some other programs that have
happened in the past, including cannabis,
where it was a situation where we would
open the block up for a period of time,
say a month or two months,
receive applications.
And then once we applications as a block,
they would be reviewed and considered
that this process is very different.
It will be done as applications come in,
they will be reviewed and information
sent back to the applicant.
And so it's not going to be done as a
block.
It's going to be done as applications are
received.
Now one thing just to to make sure
everybody is clear.
If individuals think that, Oh well,
I'm not sure if it's a full application,
so I'll just submit it.
That's going to delay it because what
will happen is we won't return it as
incomplete.
And then if they,
the resubmission date is going to be the
date that we do it, say, you know,
that we review again and we'll have to do
a full review.
And in those kinds of cases that actually
will simply delay the process.
So you'll want to make sure anybody who
is applying that they apply as completely
as possible once they're reviewing the
application and the requirements for the
application really are in the rule.
So none of that will be a surprise.
What we just have to set up is we have to
set up and we'll, we'll be working on it,
the actual application process itself.
And because they'll we'll have them
submitted electronically.
So we have to get all of those pieces set
up initially.
And so that'll just take that.
We anticipate opening that up within a
few weeks after the promulgation.
That'll also give some organizations and
people time to gather all their
information so that they're ready to
submit once we have the application open.
Does that help?
So Chris, you're on mute.
I think that clears it.
I think that clears it up quite well.
But I would like to ask if there's any
questions from other people attending.
OK,
I can't be that good that I'm actually
like answering all the questions as they
come through.
Thank you, Denali, I appreciate it.
All right.
And Denali, I have any other mic.
Hi, thank you, Dominic.
I guess I my question is who makes the
determination of the threshold of whether
the,
the breadth of amendments needs to
restart the rulemaking clock?
That's a great question, Denali.
And really it will depend upon the volume
and how many changes actually occur.
There's not a set amount of changes,
for example with regard to it.
And and so it is something that the
hearing officer does provide
recommendations where they'll recommend a
there are a lot of changes that need to
happen for example,
and I recommend that another rule hearing
occur or that these are fairly minor
changes and can move forward.
Thank you.
That's helpful.
All right.
And James you can unmute when ready.
Dominic,
just two questions on this one fees,
are you guys thinking of what is the cost
for the initial certification is and also
what is your thoughts and and plan around
that recertification and fees with that?
Thank you so much.
Thank you James.
If you mean as far As for cultivation and
with regard to testing,
part of it be based upon just the
compliance portions of the rule,
which really are you know there'll be
site inspections additional documents
being required at various points,
but really ensuring that are continuing
to move forward in a in a safe and and
and in a way that is actually consistent
with the rule.
As far as recertification,
it's not a recertification per SE,
or in this case a permit actually,
because those both the labs and the
cultivators would be issued permits on
that.
And as far as fees.
So when medical cannabis as an example
first started,
fees with regard and actually still are,
because that program was funded at that
time through the fees and so it had to be
self funding.
That's very similar to what Oregon has
had to do.
But because we were able to show and
actually talk with the legislators in
advance about the issues Oregon had,
for example,
with being able to be self-sustaining and
the issues that we had with regard to
medical cannabis in the early years,
what we were able to do is receive that
allocation from the Legislature.
And so the program itself is not
utilizing fees for the applications for
the permits.
So I hope that helps clear that up.
And again,
I should say that's because we are the
program is funded through the legislature,
not having to be self funding.
Excellent.
I don't see any other hands on that.
So I do have at least one more question.
So we get our initial rules out on
propagation and our cultivators and and
our labs begin applying for permits.
And then our next set of rules comes in
and we start changing definitions and
stuff like that.
And we'll continue to kind of go through
this process in a repeating cycle,
correct, correct.
And so for example,
this set with the cultivation and the
laboratories is the first set of rules.
The next set will be with regard to the
practitioners, clinicians,
providers and and administration.
And then the next set after that will be
with regard to locations.
So we're doing this in a, a,
a phased approach.
Once that portion is done then as the
program is rolling out and there are if
there are any concerns or any issues,
then at that time we'll continue to
initiate rulemaking and in this case rule
amendment hearings so that we can ensure
that things are covered and that anything
that we miss is added on in.
Now the other aspect of it is,
say we finish with it gets promulgated
for the cultivation and testing and while
we're in the process of the rules for the
education and administration pieces,
somebody brings up the piece that was
missed or a small amendment, for example,
to a definition that is specific to
cultivation.
Then during that rule hearing week and
that rulemaking process,
we can still amend this.
So those other two,
two proposal hearing sessions that we're
already talking about,
although we don't have dates and exact
timelines yet,
we can actually make adjustments to this
rule during those as well and the same as
we move forward.
So if during the education one after that
shortly thereafter for education and
administration,
we find there are a few changes that need
to be made that can happen during the the
portion about the locations.
The other piece that will fit into this
is of course and it's an important part
is the equity fund.
And that could fit into either of the
next set of rule hearings.
And we'll see what happens as far as the
equity committee and some of those
requests as far as the sorry everybody,
it has been a very busy and long day.
But with the equity fund,
it'll be about what those requirements
will be and how that's going to be able
to be dispersed.
And so that could fit into either of
those others or potentially if that
becomes very complex rule hearing as well.
But that again will depend on in the
other areas that we've already mentioned.
Thank you, Dominic.
I think you answered my next question in
there too.
And so it sounds like this is going to be
a continually evolving program and even a
couple years down the road,
we see something's not working well,
we can come back and and try to make
amendments to those rules.
And thank you, Chris.
Just with regard to that,
even after this set of rule hearings that
I've sort of outlined or completed,
we anticipate over that next year to two
years that there will be additional rule
hearings because there will be other
ideas or thoughts or as we've even talked
about the idea that by December we have
this so that the first patients can be
seen by December.
There may be other aspects that whether
due to complexity or additional research,
which that's needed may not be ready to
be added in yet by December.
But in order to expand the program and
more fully implement it,
we may have additional rule hearings over
that next span of time as well as
anything that may have been missed or
changes that we need to do.
Excellent.
Let's go to Gregory.
I do have a comment or a question.
All right,
And you can unmute when you're ready.
There we go.
Chris,
I just want to say I could use a solid 5
minutes of your opening 30 seconds on a
tail like this.
So thank you so much for bringing that
type of Yeah,
just bringing that to the way that this
is happening means a lot to me.
I just wanted to clarify really quick on
the recent the ARC that you covered,
Doctor Zillow.
If there are sections of this that are
clearly areas that we have not discussed
such as traceability and we know that
that is future development.
Like I'm assuming that we'll have those
sections covered.
Or are those plans to be like lumped into,
like you said,
other hearings or would that be just
something that we kind of like plan to
have in place appropriately in the
overarching schedule?
Areas that haven't been discussed would
be there,
but the traceability aspect was brought
up in the propagation meeting that that
needed to be there.
And we did model that on standard
industry practices with regard to natural
medicines to ensure that, you know,
the traceability is occurring correctly.
But yes,
if there are adjustments that need to be
made,
then that can occur whether it be
collapsing or expanding,
going into more detail regarding it
absolutely can happen.
Copy that.
So we understand that there's some level
of placeholder.
Yes, exactly.
Cool.
Love that.
Thanks.
And and just to note some people,
I may have misspoke slightly.
The public hearing the link for that,
which is in the notice for hearing,
it's not,
you don't need to actually register in
advance.
That's a link where you just show up on
it.
So my apologies if I created confusion on
that.
I'm so used to our committee meetings and
our board meetings where you do have to
register in advance.
So that is my mistake and I misspoke on
that.
So sorry if I created confusion on it.
That link is is already in that notice
for hearing and just on the day on the
24th at 9:00, you can just go and log in.
So the information for logging in is
there.
Dominic, sorry to contradict that,
but it does look like it's a registration
as requested.
And I'm guessing the reason why is
because of public comment.
You need to have the public comments
associated with a person if they're
joining hybrid online.
My my apologies then.
OK, I was correct originally then.
Thank you.
Thank you for correcting my miscorrection.
I just happened to be looking at it right
now and adding it to Apparently it's a
little bit hard to find and so I'm adding
it to our meetings page right now.
OK, thank you, Kathy.
Mm hmm.
Just to let everybody know,
Kathy is Kathy is one of our team members
who is our project manager when it comes
to IT items and is absolutely phenomenal.
So thank you Kathy.
And Johnny was also working with her
offline.
And so it those who have not met Johnny
before,
Johnny is our one of our analysts and is
absolutely phenomenal and has been the
main reason why we've been able to have
all of the different meetings that we
have.
He arranges everything and and really
helps.
So I just want to give them both shout
outs.
Absolutely.
Thanks for everybody that does all kinds
of work behind the scenes.
And so did I have it right, Kathy,
that you're going to put it on the the
meetings website along the side of the
board meetings?
And it is,
it's right up top and I just saved it.
So it should be there now.
Thank you very much.
That's excellent.
All right.
Does anybody have any other questions
about the process before we kind of dig
into or let people talk about concerns
they have with the the proposed rules?
All right.
Well then I think we'll go into that
section of it.
Denali, did you want us to begin, Chris,
just before you start though,
I do want to be clear with everybody here.
We have comments for it.
While we're we're glad to listen to them,
they do have to be submitted and I will
put that on in the chat,
be submitted through the the formal
process because the rule hearing itself
is a formal process.
So while we're glad to hear them and even
start to consider some of the comments
that are made for them to be on record,
while it's great to do it in this meeting,
they do have to go to that specific
e-mail address.
And again,
I'll put that information in the chat
here in just a minute.
We just want to make sure that's clear so
that somebody doesn't,
that nobody thinks that, oh,
by bringing it up in this meeting,
it will be a part of the public comment
of the rule hearing.
That is not the case.
It will be a part of the public comment
for this meeting,
but not for the rule itself.
So please make sure if you do have this,
those changes that you wanna submit that
way, send them to us.
And just to let everybody know on the
written comments,
it's better to do it earlier because if
it is something then that we do change,
we can announce it in the beginning of
the rule hearing and it's already in
place.
So if that's the case,
please send it to us in the next couple
of business days.
Anyway, Sorry, Chris,
I just wanted to make sure to,
to make sure everybody doesn't miss out
because they think this is OK to just say
it here and not be not at the meeting.
No, I, I appreciate that.
And I also, I guess,
should mention my intent for this meeting
was for us to kind of bring some of our
issues up collectively so that we can,
you know,
advocate for them with a united voice.
And the more of us that speak out in our
rules hearing,
the more I think the more likely there
will be to make major changes to anything
that, you know, we think needs to happen.
So that's my intention for for this next
section of what we have going on.
So again, Denali,
did you want to start us off or you want
me to go to, to somebody else?
Yeah, Chris, I'm,
I'm happy too and really grateful to you
and to the subcommittee.
I, I think it's right as we just laid out,
really helpful to have both the public
hearing opportunity,
but the engagement of the subcommittees
in that hearing process.
And so I think you're doing a great job
of modeling that back and forth.
So grateful also to the department for
committing to community feedback in the
regulatory process and the feedback that
we have offered.
I should introduce myself again,
but my name is Denali Wilson.
I am a lawyer and a policy advocate and
based in Las Cruces.
But I'm also the director of strategic
support for the Healing Advocacy Fund,
which is a nonprofit that supports state
regulated access to the psilocybin
assisted therapy.
And yes,
so our perspective healing advocacy funds
feedback that we've offered and that,
you know,
I'm happy to outline here for the for the
subcommittee is really foundational,
you know,
parts of the regulations that are
defining who can operate and how.
And I'm really grateful for the
recognition that this is an iterative
process and that, you know,
we'll be able to some of the details,
the finer details of the program will
will emerge through, you know,
what is likely to be years of
programmatic development through ongoing
rulemaking.
And it is really in critical that for the
viability of the program that early on we
get some of those foundational questions
right.
So the primarily right,
how can we create strong and protective
foundational components of who can
operate in order to to have the program
have a, a, a healthy start.
So we have offered feedback on the draft
propagation rules in four primary areas
that really maybe move to three if we
understand that as as Dominic,
you were saying,
the definition section is really just a
placeholder,
but I will talk about those sections.
So the first is prime is predatory
financing and disguised control.
And I,
I'm really grateful that the department
is prioritizing this and also willing to
consider recommendations on how to
improve the protections.
As a state,
we have just such a tremendously long
history of extractive economic
arrangements that have hurt our
communities and hurt public health.
And I I think we all share an interest in
ensuring that this space remain one of
healing and not just another place where
outside money and interest come in and
take advantage of our people and and our
resources.
The draft regulations as written attempt
to address predatory financing by pretty
broadly restricting ownership
arrangements and transfer of control.
And the approach is is a little too broad
in ways that I think will unintentionally
prohibit what are beneficial legitimate
non predatory financing arrangements,
for example,
friends and family investments.
And we we really think that the solution
is not to restrict investments broadly,
but to instead distinguish clearly and
regulate differently those who exercise
actual control over a permanent business
and those who have instead, you know,
a passive financial interest.
So we've offered suggestions that reframe
this part, you know,
the predatory financing and disguise
control parts of the code around around
that distinction in order to strengthen
protections for permit tease and the
program from people who would be bad
faith actors while preserving access to
what is a very limited capital pool in in
this space.
So,
so that's kind of the first area of of
our feedback and concerns.
There are some other related investment
rules and transfer restrictions that that
we provided feedback on as well.
Under the current draft regulations,
it's it's a little unclear whether a
party could and if so how they may invest
in a permittee without assuming the
responsibility for compliance in the
actions of a permittee.
And not that lack of,
because there's a lack of in the space
traditional investment vehicles like
banks then and traditional financing
options, the lack of clarity of how,
how one would invest without taking on
the responsibility for compliance may
unnecessarily lock out needed capital.
Again, the, the example that I'm,
I'm using is friends and family
investments.
And you know, I don't,
I don't think that's really our intention.
So additionally the the permit transfer
ban in the program.
It creates some compliance gap and
liability concerns, just as an example.
I think this is the the concern is most
poignant if we think about spouses,
children,
other people who would be left within
possession of a Schedule 1 substance
cultivation facility with no legal permit
in the case of a permit holder's death.
So when a permit holder dies,
their legal interest is going to in the
in the permanent business,
including our cultivation facilities and
contents are going to pass to their
estate to heirs, survivors.
All of that happens under ordinary state
law, but under the permit transfer ban,
those people, spouses, children,
family members may find themselves
suddenly in possession of and without any
legal responsibility with the legal
responsibility for a a facility that's
actively cultivating psilocybin mushrooms.
And now they don't have a valid permit.
So under the the draft regulations as
written,
because there is a ban on on permit
transfers,
there also is no mechanism for that
person to obtain authorization to
maintain or wind down or transfer the
operation.
So they can't legally continue to operate.
So to address that and other transfer
concerns,
we have offered to the department some
clarifying amendments to avoid that kind
of unnecessary hardship.
So those are two areas more broadly.
You know,
there are some other parts that we've
talked about,
I think more in this subcommittee equity
and access issues.
I'm going to come back to the issue I've
I've talked about from committee to
committee hearing the,
the landlord attestation issue.
And I want to start by saying something
that I think I, I'm still, you know,
relatively new to this space,
but one of the things that, you know, I,
I,
I don't think that I've recognized in the
space and deserves recognition and
acknowledgement is that New Mexico was
the first state to allow for non property
owners to operate in the cannabis
industry in the whole country.
And that was an incredibly tremendous
shift in equity and access in the
cannabis space.
And I think we should be really proud
that we were the first to model that.
And I think that it's really Dominic who
we have to, to thank for that.
And it, and it created new challenges,
right?
And we're working on figuring out how to
how to address those challenges.
But it,
it's tremendously important that we have
modelled that, you know,
you shouldn't have to be a property owner
to operate in this space.
And we want to figure out how to protect
tenants who, who do choose to participate.
And so under the current the current
draft,
landlords would be required to to produce
or tenant would have to ask their their
landlord to produce an attestation that
allows them to cultivate psilocybin in
the facility.
And the the challenge is that landlords,
even those who are supportive of their
tenants in the program,
are really unlikely to provide written
approval to engage in conduct that
remains federally illegal on their
premises.
And so I mean,
really when it comes down to it,
an attestation like that would be a
written proof in a legally binding
document of aiding and abetting in the
manufacture of Schedule 1 substances,
which exposes the landlord to civil and
criminal liability.
The the requirement also could, you know,
if our goal is to protect tenants,
we have to recognize that this kind of
attestation requirement could also create
an opening for exploitation where
landlords would,
who understand that their written
approval is required for their tenant to
engage in this program,
may use it as leverage to extract unfair
terms or higher rent from tenants.
And so we we think that the solution is
to add a lease option and that lease
option can specifically can specify that
the lease must protect a tenant
cultivators right to operate in the
program.
It may even be a good opportunity for the
the department to include model lease
language like an anti liability or what
is it called anti illegality waiver that
we'd be happy to to take a stab at
drafting with the department to make
available, right.
And then the department is in a position
to say, OK,
this level of protection or higher, right?
But it just to model what is expected and
then make similar amendments,
necessary amendments to the attestation
option.
So instead of attesting to the
cultivation of a Schedule 1 substance,
the permitting that happen right in
instead the attestation option should be
for participation in a DUH program or
something,
something a little more innocuous.
And just to wrap up the the other area of
feedback that we have offered to the
department is around some insurance
issues both for care coverage and
professional liability coverage.
These concerns really are,
are almost exclusively tied to the
definition section.
And so I understand and and appreciate
that those that should be held for for
the the appropriate regulations when they
start to to actually come into play.
And so I'm looking forward to working
with the department when those pieces are
revived and we can really work on making
sure we get it right.
Thanks, Denali.
That was awesome.
Is there a way could that people,
I have your write up and I feel like a
lot of people may have a hard time
tracking all of that if they want to make
public comment around it.
Is there a way that people could also get
a copy of the write up from you?
Is there a Yeah, yeah, I might ask.
Let's see.
So we did meet with the department
yesterday and wanted to make some after
that conversation clarifications,
especially around the pieces that we
understand are really being held for
future rule making.
So what I could do is when we make those
amendments and then share it as the
official public written comment.
I,
I know it'll be made available through
the department,
but maybe there's a way to share it
directly through the subcommittee.
I'm saying it with this inflection as a
question because maybe someone can tell
me whether that's possible.
Johnny, can we,
if she emails us something,
can we send that out as part of to the
registrants?
Yeah, Yeah, I can, I can e-mail to yeah,
everybody registered for this meeting.
Is that what you were asking, Denali?
Yeah.
Perfect.
OK, cool.
So I'll make the changes that that we
talked about and then I will send it to
you and to Johnny.
Is that right?
Yes, please.
OK, awesome.
And to the official thing because it's
not official until I do that.
OK, yes, thank you, Denali.
I know you have a comment.
Greg.
I heard you try to get in there,
but James Brown has had his hand up for a
while.
So I'm going to go to him real quick and
then I'm going to cut to you anyway,
James.
Thank you, Chris.
Just real quick on my end,
it's around that dual ownership.
Can you guys explain and just expand on
that so that I can extrapolate my opinion
and submit something as far as that goes?
Are you saying 1 permentee for each
business or the permentee can own both of
those types of businesses as far as being
a producer and a laboratory if they
wanted to be?
And again,
with that licensee or Permentee sorry be
restricted if they wanted to be either a
facilitator, a a guide,
something else as far as a practitioner
or any other permit that was required
through the DoH process.
Thank you.
Just for clarification,
I think you're talking about the section
735.2.9,
the general permittee requirements,
dual ownership prohibited.
Is that what you're talking about, James?
Exactly, Chris, just write it there.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Do you wanna talk about that,
Dominic or I feel like I can take this on
too.
I, I, let me take a, a shot at it.
So, James,
the way the rules are written currently
and is essentially that there is not dual
ownership allowed.
And a lot of that is due to conflict of
interest.
That is actually one of the lessons
learned that we have had from other
programs and that that it creates
potential issues and concerns.
For example,
you don't want the same person
cultivating or the same entity
cultivating and then testing.
And because then what happens and how
much more difficult does it become to
track down if, for example,
there are falsified or adulter tests and
things like that.
Similar with regard to the same
individuals offering the administration
and someone who is cultivating or again,
even testing.
That creates a lot of conflicts of
interest.
What Denali and and and team are
suggesting and which are legal legal team
is looking at is that in some of the
ownership,
so the permits would still go to the
could only go to the one and no dual
ownership in that regard.
But that in order to allow for some more
flexible investing and especially for
startups because we recognize similar as
with cannabis,
because of the schedule one status that
you can't get loans or you know,
or items through banks.
And many private investors say absolutely
not in that regard,
that where you might be able to get
investors who are willing to, you know,
to invest and help with the start up
money.
And that may actually be involved with
regard to permitting that you could still
invest to a small amount and so still
help with some of those other entities
and those other permits,
but they still would not be able to have
controlling interest, decision making,
those sort of things,
those sort of aspects.
And Denali,
please correct me if I mean if I'm
explaining this either too broad and
generally or if I missed the boat,
but that's my understanding at this point.
Is that correct, Denali?
Yeah, Well,
and I think you've captured it really
well.
Really what what we recommended,
and this goes back to what I was saying
about distinguishing between 2,
two different classes of, of sorry,
how did I say it,
tiers of ownership and control.
And so if we distinguish instead between
those who exercise actual control over a
permanent business and those who have,
you know,
more passive financial interests,
what what we've recommended is an
inclusion of a definition of a,
a true party in interest,
which is something that exists in other
spaces that we can look to.
That's really what we're talking about.
We're talking about actual control over a
business that could be used to unfairly
influence the market.
And and I think when it comes to dual
ownership, the recommendation would be OK.
You can't be a true party in interest in
two separate entities, but you could,
as you just put it,
Dominic be a minority investor in in more
than one.
Does that answer your question, James?
Yeah, Chris,
just one thing is with that just kind of
limits business.
I've been,
I was in the breed business and I've been
in pharmacy business for a long time.
And some of this is gonna restrict,
you're causing some choke,
choke points here.
And I just think that that's something to
for for us to come up with some comments
on.
And I mean,
it might be just a hard stop there,
which is fine.
I just wanted to know, you know,
if you're a rural,
let's say you're one of these little
communities like Farmington,
there might only be one person or one
group that we'll be able to provide these
services even from a growing point.
If they wanna be able to do that locally,
it'd have to be somebody completely
different.
And so I just like as a nonprofit, I,
I just think it restricts some of that.
That's all.
Thank you.
Yeah.
And I,
I know we've heard similar comments in
the past, but I,
I tend to agree with Dominic on,
on this one that the conflict of interest
kind of outweighs some of that.
And and also, you know,
a lot of people are going to be in the
same boats where they have to,
they have to drive to get their products
tested or, you know,
they're going to have to drive to get to
get their product long distances.
And so that's just going to be part of
running a program in rural areas.
And we've done a lot to try to minimize
the effects of that throughout this
process.
So go ahead, Dominic.
Yeah, thank you, Chris.
And and sort of answer that as well,
James,
is that's also a part of where the equity
and access fund comes into play,
which wasn't something that was available
in some of the former programs.
And so having that,
that the part of the idea on that is to
help minimize those potential issues,
especially in rural frontier areas.
And so there may be other ways to assist
that doesn't create that conflict of
interest.
And so those are parts of what will be
being looked at,
especially with regard to the equity
piece.
So I hope that helps as well.
All right,
Any further comment on that section?
I want to thank Denali and Victoria's
Centenovic for coming up with those
amazing rules.
And you know,
I noticed one thing that we discussed a
lot in propagation that's absent is the
sunset clause.
I got to bring this up and,
and from meetings with Chris Woodward,
it's, you know,
I think that was a a stretch from the
beginning to get that put in there.
But after speaking with Victoria about
some of the predatory financing laws that
she wants to, yeah,
implement with the Department of Health
here, she assured me that, you know,
it's gonna go a long way to protect our
local community.
And, and she's very sharp and I, I,
I trust her on that.
And I'm not a lawyer, so I,
I really can't speak to the efficacy,
but she's both her and, and all are,
are working really hard to,
to protect our local cultivators and,
and testers and everybody involved in
this program.
So I want to thank you both very much for
all the support on that.
All right, Next up,
I also want to thank Greg Gregory Evans
for coming to just about every committee
meeting, I think,
and being involved in every aspect of
this program.
You're amazing, Sir.
And would you like some time to talk
about what you see here?
Did we lose him?
No.
I'm here.
Thank you.
Yeah.
I want to be as thorough as possible
without boring everybody to death.
I think the first thing I'm going to do
here is considering I.
So I have a fairly robust analysis and I
have made some.
I've made a three page and a 16 page
print out version.
The three page is just high level what
we're looking at without the arguments
and the reasons behind things.
And then the 16 page kind of covers some
of the more.
Nuanced.
Why am I recommending this?
Does it go back to this decision made in
this specific meeting?
This is what was voted on by the Advisory
Board or whatever.
Just my primary goal is to get this
document in alignment with the vision of
the committee and the board,
understanding that much of this needs to
be sanity checked through layers of
review, government,
and ideally when we get to this section,
actually a biochemist and some scientists
that are experts in some of the testing
stuff.
So from a high level,
I wanted to just kind of get some
feedback.
Do you guys want me to just burn through
a list of everything that I've got here?
I have around 20.
I have exactly 29 recommendations.
A good chunk of those are definitions in
set in three categories,
but I just wanted to know,
do you want me to just run through it or
do you want me to go into detail and on
the sections as I go through?
How about we?
Run through it.
And it could this also be something that
we could attach to that same e-mail,
Johnny Yeah, sure.
OK.
And then we can we can attach the your
document to it.
And that way if people want to do the
deep dive,
they can they can kind of go and do it on
their own.
Does that sound good, Greg?
Yeah.
Anyone who wants to see the actual
detailed language that is not behind a
firewall can click the link.
It's a public website.
Anybody can view that.
And then I'll Polish up the,
the shortened PDFs for some,
for like official submission, you know,
hopefully today or tomorrow and get those
too.
So did you include the link on the chat
for people to do their deep dive?
I forgot to press send.
OK.
I'm really exhausted.
Thank you.
Is,
is it possible for me to share or is it
better for me to just talk?
Yeah.
Can we can we let him share Johnny if he
wants to?
Yeah.
Show a screen.
OK, let's see.
Do you have the option up by the mic?
Yep.
Do you see the share thing?
OK, cool.
Yeah, one second.
And just as a reminder, Greg,
since you don't usually have that
capacity, whatever you do,
do not click on the yellow end event
button.
It's next to share.
If that does happen,
the meeting is over and that's we're,
we're not able to rejoin.
So please do not do that.
Thank you very much.
Unfortunately,
I'm in way too many teams meetings for
the Department of Public Safety and I'm
seeing it happen.
Let's see,
I'm going to constrain this to just this,
and I think this is it.
So let me see if I can do this.
I'm still figuring this program out,
but it's pretty great when it works.
This is a working draft,
yadda yadda yadda.
Some stuff about who I am,
why we're doing this.
This is really comment,
all these comments are to align the
document with the intention of the
committees.
And then there are a few things where we
need to do some sanity around some
science.
So under definitions I have 3 sections,
the amendments,
the gaps and then the the stuff that we
don't need.
I think the stuff we don't need is pretty
well known.
So we don't really need spending time in
there.
So I'm just running through it really
quick.
The definition of inoculate is obscenely
incorrect and I have provided a
suggestion down here that states
inoculate means the process of
introducing spores, mycelium,
or spawn into growth medium.
The definition of psilocybin based on
several factors of how the rule is
written should be broken out in to
include solocin,
whereas and and we can you can remove the
chemical weights,
but it's might be worth having them in
there.
But it essentially it just breaks those
two apart.
Cultivation manufacturer definitions.
This was something that took me a while
to kind of like wrap my head around,
but based on all the conversations that
we had and the nature of the final
product and the pathway to get there,
the recommendation that I have is to
define cultivation as the means of
inoculation, growing,
main maintenance and maintenance of
psilocybin.
Producing mushrooms through harvest
process would carry you from drying,
homogenization or preparing processed
material for storage.
And then manufacture would be putting it
into sachets or capsules.
There's quite a bit of reasoning in here
to go over,
but I'll skip through that unless anybody
wants me to come back.
I do think that's one second.
Yeah.
Can you can you enlarge your text?
I have it on my side screen,
but there's no way I can see it on my own.
So I'm.
I'm fairly sure if other people are
following along,
they might not be able to see it.
There we go.
That's better.
Thank you.
Thank you for asking.
Like I would love nothing more for this
presentation to go full screen,
but I've tried everything.
I would like to come back to the
committee for consensus on defining if we
should remove the term convert,
because the term convert insinuates a
process of extraction and all of the
other processes that we require for this
specific format of the program that are
covered with these three definitions.
So moving on,
there was a lot of artifacts from whoever
copied and pasted this from the cannabis
terminology that didn't clear the term
lot.
So there's a fairly exhaustive mapping of
how that needs to be cleaned up later on
here,
but essentially the recommendation is to
strike 7H5.
The homogenization requirement is
resolved by the amendment or the amended
batch definition C, Item 8 on C7C,
which specifies batches must be fully
homogenized prior to testing on potency.
There's a little bit of confusion in how
that was written and I think it will be
more accurate to say potency means
concentration of psilocybin and analyt
specified in Table 2 of 19-G in a sample
of a batch lot or see we need to clear
that lot or product measured and
expressed in milligrams per gram.
And this kind of ties back to that
conversation about concentration potency
being locked into psilocybin and then
later in the like psilocybin equivalency
and then later and I think this might
actually still need some work,
but defining that the silosin equivalency
can be included on those labels.
But like the cornerstone is the single
singular psilocybin equivalency
measurement,
and defining how that is measured is
something that we may still need to get
into the weeds about,
but not necessarily today.
The definition of mycelium was wrong,
and I've corrected it.
Mycelium means the vegetative body of a
fungus composed of a network of
filamentous structured called hyphy.
If you want definition of why it's wrong,
that's there.
And then This is why we should consider
adopting different language.
I'm open to interpretation,
but this is scientifically incorrect.
Fruiting bodies definition.
Same issue here, correct?
A better or more correct definition would
be spore bearing reproductive structures
of a fungus including the cat stem and
associated tissues.
Lot hierarchy replaced with batch as a
single production unit.
As we discussed at nauseam during the
committee's,
this is how I want to map this structure
out.
We've got all these definitions,
definition of the problem.
Basically the term lot does not appear
anywhere in the adopted propagation
outline.
We're moving to batch based on scope of
production,
where if we were producing thousands of
pounds at a time,
we would have to separate lot and batch.
But the mapping and downstream sections
of how those corrections would need to be
adopted if this was or need to be
adjusted if this logic was fully adopted
into this document are mapped out here.
It has every instance of lot and how it
should be corrected to reflect back to
the term batch.
Batch also being was, I think,
I'm not sure if I passed it,
but batch wasn't defined as one kilogram
as discussed.
And so I've included that in here as well
with the four week window of harvest
cycles.
So the official recommendation is to
strike convert here.
Hey Greg.
Yeah, Sorry if I got lost.
Yeah.
Can I,
I just want to ask Dominic one question.
Is there a reason we we brought the term
lot into this?
Because I,
I don't remember ever talking about it or
having a need for it either.
Yeah, it actually is,
is part of the normal rule process.
If you have everything all as batch,
it ends up actually being extraordinarily
confusing because you're at different
stages.
And so it's really just designating and
determining at what stage of the process
it is.
And that's why the batches at that
particular point and the lots actually
fit with regard to especially
homogenization.
That's really where that is.
And then product lot is a regular term
that is utilized within industries,
various industries when you have product
lots.
And so that's just why that particular
one is there.
To be honest,
if we could have utilized even a
different term to distinguish between
those different stages,
that would have been even better,
quite frankly.
But making it all just batch would then
mean that everything would fit under that
batch definition,
which makes it very difficult and you
wouldn't be able to actually distinguish
which batches, you know what batch.
What exactly does batch mean without
having it all separated out into
different definitions anyway?
And a lot of that is just semantics and
not necessarily part of it.
But I will address the one part about the,
the thousand, I'm sorry,
the the kilogram aspect,
the reason that wasn't included under the
actual batch item,
the 1 kilogram cap is because that was
done for the testing purposes,
which was the main discussion.
And as we were talking with the various
laboratories and other areas with regard
to it, that was part of that suggestion.
So we didn't keep that as far as the
spirit and the intent behind having that
limitation on the batch.
It's just actually not included in the
definition, but in the sample size.
Yeah, thank you, Dominic.
I I'm just wanting to be clear.
So that way we're, you know, if I,
if I advocate for this,
I know what I'm advocating for.
And yeah, same.
And I think that's new information for me
as well.
So thank you for walking through that.
Absolutely.
My pleasure.
Just off the cuff,
it might be if we have to use lot like if
a batch is a single inoculation of a
product across multiple whatever
containers and a batch is all of the
harvests over the course of four weeks,
a single flush could represent.
So a single flush is harvest could
represent a lot and then you could
homogenize that lot and then get 4 lots
in a month or whatever and combine those
up together as a batch.
But I also think that for testing
purposes like the, the more, the,
the more product we batch together in a
single testing event,
the greater our consistency across known
dosing variables will be.
So I don't know if there's even time to
really get into that,
but trying to stay out of the weeds on
that today,
but I'll probably do some rewriting on
this.
Oh, thanks, Craig.
Yeah, yeah, totally.
And then that covers all of the
adjustments that I had marked.
And then the there are 4 gaps that I
wanted to identify.
We refer to spawn all over the document.
So we need to define spawn.
Spawn is substrate material colonized by
mycelium that is used as an inoculant to
initiate mushroom cultivation in bulk
growth medium.
That is very important to have as a
definition because of what's written here.
Next,
we do not define certificate of analysis.
I don't know if that was intentional,
but if you wanted to include the
definition for the purposes of this
program,
this is the text that I would recommend.
We do not have a definition for shelf
life or stability.
And I'm kind of like either or, you know,
there could be value in having it and
value in not having it.
There's some level of ambiguity that like
if we have stability and shelf life tied
to variables like are retesting cadence
that end up shifting,
it just means a lot of things that we
have to cascade changing, cascading.
Yeah,
I mentioned exhausted and then items to
defer.
Just let us scan through these.
I think if any of these aren't already
known, I'd be surprised.
But yeah, that's in the definitions.
Now for the fun stuff.
How are we feeling?
I did a lot of thinking about sample size.
The initial recommendation is that we
lock it to 1 to 5G after looking at some
of the analytes that were introduced per
the recommendation or per the per the per
the document that we're reviewing that
we're not expected analyt requirements.
I think that the logic would be much
better to defer to the Sops of the
testing facilities.
And then if we need to constrain the
rules around, you know,
like I think we have a pretty good
coverage of control on approving those.
SO PS so if we trust the testing
facilities,
I don't think deferring that amount to
them is outside of reason.
There is a potential based on increased
testing panels requested below,
which we'll look at next,
that it could be up to 1 to 10% or or
like 1 to 10 grants depending on how many,
like hydration tests and other fungal
panels and other bacteria stuff that's
included.
So we'll get into those details below.
But I put this definition together in
hopes of like containing the spirit of
what the intended goal of the committee
was.
Now for the fun words.
The let's see if I can pull up the I
don't want to bore everybody with science,
the documents available to read,
but there are a lot of things being
required by this in testing that could
push unit like individual testing
instances well over $2000.
I feel like I want to be very respectful
to the people who put this document
together,
but I don't think enough attention was
put on this and I don't think it was
reviewed by a mycologist or.
Anybody who under Yeah, anyways,
I don't want to a lot of it it.
I spend a lot of time researching this
and getting to the like the details and
all of this has full review documentation
with bibliographies if anybody's
interested in seeing any of that.
The four organisms that should be removed
from routine testing are Chica toxin or
Shiga toxin producing E coli,
which is different than most of the E
Coli's that we standard test for.
Stand in a standard panel.
Clostridium botulinium,
Pseudomonas auruginosa,
auruginosa and tricoderma is not a human
pathogen and it's commonly found in
fungal like it's yeah,
it's it's going to be there.
So this would kill all good,
good number of tests wouldn't allow
things to market.
There's a bunch of stuff in here that
would block product to market.
That's probably one of the least
impactful ones,
but it's just it doesn't need to be in
there.
So I would recommend adding to the
provision to not require testing for
Shiga toxin,
E coli clustered in botulinism or
botulinum and Pseudomonas arugenosa,
Trichoderma Aspergillus, nisure,
Aspergillus tereus.
The two aspergillus could be triggered
for quality control testing if the
department felt like they really need to
to include them at some level.
But overall,
if anybody has the patience to read all
this stuff,
it boils down to unnecessary testing.
High like high cost with low reward.
And if we're just trying to flex that
we're testing a lot,
I think that this price tag that could
potentially even be doubled based on
further panels that we'll discuss is a
bit absurd.
And I do have a full document breaking
down the price.
The cost analysis of all of this 19 E
yeast molds threshold 20 Cfus is
literally unachievable for dried fungal
products.
It's unprecedented.
And the only reason I can see that this
would ever be here is if somebody forgot
a comma and three zeros.
There's absolutely no world in which
testing for yeast mold at sub 20 CFU is
passable like literally mold as fungus.
So it just doesn't make sense.
All these details are too many words for
me to go through right now,
but I'll get to recommendation.
I'm in the table.
Adjust the CFU to 100,000 CFU per gram,
which matches most states cannabis,
Whereas New Mexico's cannabis is at 1000,
which is a wonderful barrier for that
product where you are inhaling that
product after it's been combusted.
Whereas these types of materials that
we're testing for don't have nearly the
same impact on a gut Biome.
If I'm being very honest,
the actual barrier could be 100 billion
parts and it was still be safe.
Just considering the context of what
we're testing and why we're testing that.
I don't want to bore everybody.
I'm sure everybody's most people are
asleep and we're I'm running way long.
Almost there.
The depth,
the detail on Aspergillus reporting.
The document requires binary detection.
Easiest way to walk through this is to
just say like those are not things we
need to be testing for the like.
Some of these tests look like they came
from like and food testing rather than
something that is related to the product
that we're discussing.
The binary action result it,
this is a test that will probably prevent
90% of produced materials from making it
to market.
That's a very rough off the cuff.
I don't have a document to defend the 90%,
but this would get in the way of a lot of
product making it to market,
be a huge strain on producers and the
entire system moving on.
Done with all the bacterias and stuff.
Residual solvents.
I recommend we moved it remove this
because of the scope of our our program
doesn't allow for any type of extractions.
Therefore there wouldn't be any residual
solvents left to test for.
If we're trying to prevent edge cases
where people are doing things,
nefarious things,
I think we would need to approach that
from a different perspective rather than
providing a burden on all producers.
I'm glad I don't have to read this whole
thing.
This is an interesting 1 water content
testing.
I would encourage the department to kind
of read through this in depth because
this is, this was kind of just this one.
This one triggered some learning for me
and some deep thought on potency and
viability over time.
And Chris, again, like,
please interrupt me if I'm taking too
much time.
I think we're still good.
I don't.
Where are you at?
Here.
Let me look at you.
I think I can wrap it up.
I think you got a couple more pages.
Yeah, you're good.
Yeah.
The last five pages are mostly blank.
OK,
so water content shall be determined by
the loss on drawing and shall not be
exceeded by 10%.
Wait.
The water content result expressed as
percentage shall not be reported on COA
or shall be reported on the COA.
This allows us to track when we do,
when we trigger retesting if our potency
variants is is affected by water
hydration variants as opposed to alkaloid
degradation.
It's an important thing to track if we
insist that our target so,
so we're we have to test for LOD,
any lab is going to test LOD before they
do any sort of analysis anyways.
So if we put push that drying limit to
the lower end of it, the 8 to 12 range,
we will have less risk of degradation
over time across the board.
We won't know the efficacy of that until
we have a year or two of data attached to
that is the upstream microbial control.
So in way too many words.
Yeah.
Pardon the pause.
Yeah, go ahead.
So I just wanted to ask Dominic if we had
reached out to any of the labs in
Colorado or Oregon to kind of verify the
requirements that we put in and make sure
they were kind of in keeping with what we
were we're going for.
And not that I don't trust your,
your work, but I always, you know,
say trust, but verify, right?
Like,
and if that's something that we should
verify everything.
Yes, Chris, actually we have.
And some of these items, for example,
I would agree with Greg on if it weren't.
We are also looking at potential
contaminants from growth medium and from
sources.
And so that's actually why that testing
is there.
Yes,
if everybody did everything in a
completely clean sterilized environment,
many of these wouldn't be necessary.
However,
the reason they're there is to ensure the
safety.
And this is true for testing it with
regard to any products, food,
other medications, things like that.
And remember, this is a medication,
so it does have a higher standard than
simply looking at it from the food stand,
food product or item.
And so we do have to ensure to keep that.
Now that doesn't mean that we won't
continue to look at them.
And,
and as we've said throughout the life
cycle of the of the program,
we'll be continuing to look at testing at
measures and really ensuring that things
are going to be done appropriately.
And one thing that I want to make sure I
mention is that there is within the
within the rule the ability of the
program to delay a particular test or set
of tests.
If we do find out as we move forward that
it's something that the capacity just
isn't there or that it becomes too
burdensome.
And so that those are all things that
we've put in in order to ensure that we
are still able to have testing so that
items are safe.
So long as it is done,
you know that things are safe,
but if they become too burdensome,
that we can reduce that down so long as
we ensure it's still safe.
Yeah, I hope that helps.
Yeah, absolutely.
And part of the reason I request or
suggesting or offering adding this new
provision for controlling the water
activity levels is to prevent against
those high risk microbials that actually
do 'cause issues.
So basically in lay terms,
I'm saying make sure the mushrooms are
actually dry.
And by actually dry,
there's math and proof of that,
of that dry, the state of dehydration.
And what that will do is it will.
Where did my words go?
Here we go.
Setting the threshold at .
6 places the product below the growth
range of every Organism of concern in the
panel, including xerophilic molds,
Aspergillus, Flavius, aflatoxin,
the aflatoxin producer retained in the
amended panel.
So I think by implementing this,
that helps us reduce the risk on the rest
of the panel,
therefore increasing the product quality
across the entire program and reducing
burden on everybody honestly.
Yeah, leave it there.
Retesting cadence,
I just kind of went back to.
So I believe it was left in at 5 to 6
months.
We kind of had that conversation about
putting that at 12 months.
So if that is really our intention,
this is to align the document with the
recommendation of the board.
If the if that was changed intentionally,
I'm more than happy to sit in whatever
camp needs to be supported and that's
about it.
I have some labeling and potency stuff.
I'll just let people read through that at
will.
I will vocalize that I'm not a huge fan
of the some of the terminology that's
being adopted that was made-up.
It doesn't feel in line with most
industry standards, but I can.
The math is there.
I'm fine with it.
Storage and shelf life, due process,
all that.
Yeah, that's it.
Thank you for putting up with my 35
minutes.
No, thanks for going deep.
These are some of the questions we need
to ask and I'll be reading and looking
into some of this stuff,
so I appreciate it.
Greg.
Next up, Greg, can you tick me?
How do I stop?
Sherry, Get Me Out of here.
Oh, here I can.
And push the yellow button, right?
Oh, no.
OK, let's see.
There we go.
I think.
Oh, wow.
Did that still not do it?
No, that that did.
That's correct.
Correct on that.
Yep.
Yeah.
It just it took it a second online.
Yeah.
Cool.
Thank you, Johnny, and thank you, Greg.
Thank you, Johnny.
And Next up, Brett,
did you have anything that you wanted to
add that's not been added so far?
Whoops.
Sorry.
Go ahead, Brett, whenever you're ready.
There we go.
OK.
Your mic should be enabled now.
OK, great.
Can you guys hear me?
OK, cool.
Yeah, thanks.
Thanks a lot again to everyone at the
Department of Health, Chris,
everyone else that.
Yeah, they contributed.
Yeah.
Denali had a lot of good stuff, Greg.
Yeah.
Credibly thorough, man.
Nice.
Nice job.
And yeah,
I know you've been deep in in all these.
I don't have a a ton to add, so mine.
Yeah.
So my name is Brett Phelps.
For those of you that I don't know
already,
I'm an attorney here in Las Vegas,
NM have mostly been recently have have
started working on some of this with the
Psychedelic Bar Association.
So we don't have any financial interest
in this,
but that is a group of lawyers across the
country that yeah are just interested in
these these policies and things.
So I have been involved with them some
lately.
I believe we have met with,
have met with Dominic and some of the,
the DoH people.
So, so I don't have a lot new to add.
I did just want to kind of second a few
things mostly around,
around Denali's comments,
specifically the, the,
the actual control and the ownership.
I,
I really get what the department is
trying to do there and, you know,
protecting people and,
and making sure that there's transparency.
But I think getting a better
understanding of what's considered actual
control versus a, you know, a passive, a,
a passive financial investor can,
can satisfy those goals while,
while still allowing these, you know,
types of financial arrangements that
really there's not a lot of places you
can go to get financing for these,
you know, for these types of these,
these types of endeavors.
And so, you know,
since you can't go to a bank or get a
standard type of business loan, I think,
you know, allowing some of these in,
in ways that I,
I think are addressed pretty thoroughly
in the, in the, the document provided by,
by Denali and some of that.
So I won't go into too much detail other
than I think and, and we'll provide a,
a more thorough written one as well.
But I think getting an idea of what's
actual control versus just what's,
you know,
a passive financial and investment.
And I think they have have offered some,
some ways to do that.
The dual ownership.
I, I think I,
I totally get the labs right,
not having people involved in labs and
other entities.
Beyond that, I don't think that the,
the conflict of interest is really,
you know,
I think that's where the main conflict of
interest concern arises.
And so I think limiting people from being
involved in,
in production and laboratories at the
same time makes sense.
But but in other, you know, in other ways,
I don't,
I don't think it necessarily I don't
think the,
the regulations as they are now outweigh
the the potential benefits of people
being able to support on multiple,
you know, multiple businesses.
Again,
if we have that actual control more
clearly defined,
then I think that can help eliminate that
or allow that to to not be the the
potential conflict of interest.
Another big one that we've, you know,
come across is the,
how we're going to deal with the lease
agreements and the, you know,
the language that I think in,
in the current proposed rule is just
going to be really, really tough for,
for people to do.
I just don't see a lot of property owners
wanting to put down on write in writing
that they are allowing somebody to,
you know, essentially violate federal law.
So I I think there may be some other ways
around that or something that something
that can.
I, I,
I know how a lot of that happened in the
cannabis space when that came on board
and people, you know,
I get the having that protection in place
for the potential permit tease.
But I think there's maybe a a better way
that that we could look at doing that
that would not not be so,
so restrictive there maybe something like
language about, you know,
to participate in licensed Department of
Health activities, that type of thing.
I think is, is possible.
And then the other, you know,
the other kind of big one that's that's
within this this purview is the the the
flat out basically ban on the transfer of
the the licenses.
You know,
I think I think Denali brought up a good
point of what do you do if if somebody
passes away and then the license
essentially goes away with them and the
people that are left with the, you know,
left with the infrastructure that don't
have a license.
Also,
I think it's just AII think it's going to
be a major sort of discourage, yeah,
discouraging to people to get into the
industry if they are into this,
into this program,
if they don't have any kind of real exit
plan, right.
It's really hard to to picture, you know,
if you're going to set up and and run a
business and you eventually want to get
out of that business to not be able to,
to sell your license is really,
really puts people in a in a tough bind.
So I think on that, you know,
not not allowing it without department
approval, I think would be a way that,
you know, we can, we can maintain that.
I understand the,
the transparency issues and wanting to
wanting to know what's going on
financially with these,
these organizations,
but I just see a flat out ban as as being,
you know, real problematic.
And so I think if, if,
if that's something the department has
control over, has approval over,
then it would satisfy the,
the concerns that that I think the rule
is,
is based around while still allowing that
flexibility for,
for business owners and and operators.
One, one other one,
I know this has been discussed and I, it,
it may be kind of a,
a dead issue at this point,
but I just wanted to bring it up.
Is the,
that at this point only the homogenize
that,
that the product all has to be
homogenized.
You know,
if we're looking at more of the the non,
I guess non non western traditional
medicine applications,
if we're looking at, you know,
more other types of, you know,
indigenous based practices or or ways to,
you know, to provide this medicine.
I think allowing, you know,
allowing the non homogenized product or
medicine to be consumed would would
really again fall under those those
equity concerns in the big,
the big concerns there.
So that one,
I don't know if the department is yeah,
that they may have already reviewed that
and decided that was going to be a no go.
But that was that was one other thing,
because I know we have been trying to
figure out how are we going to include as
many people to participate in this as as
possible,
who's going to be able to provide the the
medicine.
And I think allowing that that open,
you know, having other options there,
I think is is important those.
So those are the those are the big ones.
Like I said, I think that I think,
you know,
Denali's written out comments really get
into the details of what this could look
like.
But I just wanted to really 2nd and
support the,
the issues that they brought up and
specifically the ones that myself and,
and some of my colleagues with the
Psychedelic Bar Association have
identified as well.
So that's,
that's about all I have right now.
Again,
thanks to all of you guys putting in all
this work.
And yeah,
excited to see where things go next week.
So thanks, Chris.
Thank you, Brett.
Yeah,
I hope eventually we figure out some way
to get a waiver or something through for
people that engage with the mushroom
directionally.
You know,
I was up in Colorado for my training
recently in a experiential session and I
did 3 grams of, you know, in,
in whole mushroom form.
And I was thinking about Matthew A
wherever he is and,
and several other people that kind of
brought that up through the process.
And, and I had a beautiful journey.
And,
and I I do think that eventually needs to
be part of it,
but I don't know if it's going to make it
in right away.
James.
Yeah.
So I wonder if we could even get them
protected.
Just to follow up on that, Chris, I think,
you know, on the permit,
EI can totally agree with a laboratory
being a separate permit E than a producer.
I just really want the the department,
you guys to really consider the thought,
you know,
get behind that sharing that permit with,
let's say that you're a retreat or that
now you're a service center or whatever
terminology that we define it as.
I just think that you should be able to
have the ability to have a a production
license.
And again,
there's something spiritually behind that
on that push.
I really do think that there's a
connection with growing something and
having people it being tested and make
certain sources is all controlled and all
that.
That's fine from a third party.
But then bringing it back to that center
and then experiencing that what you grew.
And I think, you know,
we're kind of forgetting that.
And I just wanted to bring that up as a
strong point to say there's a spiritual
side of this that we're kind of
forgetting.
And I think that would allow us to be one
of the two,
but also have a center or retreat or one
of those other type of licenses to
provide those administrations.
Thank you.
Does anybody else have any comments or
concerns or things that they've seen in
the regulations that they want to want to
bring up in this space and well,
there appears to consider advocating for?
We have Jarvis, Jarvis Webster,
please introduce yourself and let us know
what's on your mind.
Can you hear me?
Yep.
Yeah.
OK.
I wanted to comment on some of the
rulemaking that Gregory Evans was talking
about.
I'm not sure that I'm clear on what lot
and batch means,
but the four weeks time will not
accurately give you one 2-3 or four
flushes like you were talking about in
that it's more like 8 weeks time.
And there's some real concerns with
Aspergillus because that's black mold.
I know that it's somewhat safe in food
ingredients,
but if there's black mold growing in your
spawn and it grows into your mushrooms,
it's really dangerous.
Some of the other pathogens that you,
that you talked about in the stuff you
went over are less safe than I, I, I, I,
I guess I disagree.
I don't think they're quite as safe as
you talked about.
There should be a limitation on parts per
million for some of those contaminants.
I guess that's not a question,
it's a comment.
Thank you.
Jarvis.
Anybody else have anything they want to
add?
Right.
I appreciate all of you bringing your
voices to the space.
And I will be at the meeting on the 24th
and I'm looking forward to seeing anybody
else who joins us there and looking
forward to hearing all your comments and
that I know Dominic's going to be there.
Are you going to be there, Jorge?
Awesome.
So at least the three of us will be there
and hopefully we get others too.
So we will have the hearing officer and
the the attorney representing the
department, Chris Woodward, will be there.
So there'll be at least five of us in
person, Chris.
So, but seriously, I, I, I echo that.
I do hope that other people are there so
that they can one,
hear some of the modifications based upon
the comments that we already have
received.
And also to be able to express your own.
You know,
we want to make sure that this is an open
space for people to be able to express
their thoughts, their ideas,
and so that we can actually ensure that
we have the best program possible.
So I just want to thank everybody for
also bringing some of this up.
But,
and I put it in the chat again is if you
do want to submit comments,
remember while we're listening to you
here and we are taking note of it,
it is not official comment on the rules
unless it is submitted as as required in
the notice.
And I did put that portion about where
you can submit it either electronically
to jacob.clark@doh.nm.
gov or the postal address.
So.
So thank you everybody.
I appreciate it.
Thank you all.
And this is probably the end of the
propagation committee,
so take care of yourselves and I
appreciate you all and I'm looking
forward to seeing you on the 24th and
then the other committees.
So thank you, everyone.
Thank you everyone.